<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mets:mets xmlns:mets="http://www.loc.gov/METS/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <mets:dmdSec xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" ID="ie-dmd">
    <mets:mdWrap MDTYPE="DC">
      <mets:xmlData>
        <dc:record xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
          <dc:title> Optimizing Reinforcement</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Adam Orlinski</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Klaas  De Rycke</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Moritz Heimrath</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2022-02-15</dc:date>
          <dcterms:isPartOf>Open Access E-Journals/TIB OP/OCP/2021/1/1/</dcterms:isPartOf>
          <dcterms:abstract xml:lang="en_US">The combination of parametric modelling with structural analysis prompted new synergies between designing and engineering. The connection of structural calculation models such as Karamba3d to algorithmic modelling platforms such as Grasshopper3d allowed to embed tools for analysis and simulation into the environment of creative design processes. This way structural analysis advanced from its single sided calculation “duty” towards participation in design language of articulated structural expression.  3d-concrete-printing serves as a great new territory to apply the potential of real-time parametric structural analysis in the built environment of rapid prototyping and robotic fabrication. While 3d-printed-concrete rapidly advanced in technology and empiric know-how, so also grew the ambition to utilize them for larger purposes and bigger building projects. Known requirements such as structural integrity according to building code, interfaces for construction or waterproofing pose clear challenges for further realizations. In order to develop 3d-concrete-printing to its full potential all challenges must serve as opportunities to dissect and rethink established norms and practices, and to construct a new interdisciplinary rule book for an emerging building technology. In this field working through challenges via prototypes serve as great basis for development and allows for an applied discourse within the wider community. Furthermore to address challenges a flexible toolbox for structural analysis such as Karamba3d offers the potential to serve as an open instrument for structural analysis and to promote 3d-concrete-printing within that interdisciplinary effort to its next level. On the one hand the tool enables to suggest customized and optimized rebar layouts which could support the development of 3D-concrete-printing further. By enabling this more customizable calculation and tailored real time feedback for complex structures, solutions can develop more structurally informed. On the other hand, recent developments with Karamba3D within our office of Bollinger+Grohmann have shown the possibility of real time feedback loops between the physical printing process and the digital calculation model. Both developments show the potential that material systems can be optimized towards specific patterns or values of forces, or structures can be evaluated in real time for their load bearing capacity while hardening during printing.</dcterms:abstract>
          <dcterms:issued>2022</dcterms:issued>
          <dcterms:modified>2022-02-15 08:22:42</dcterms:modified>
          <dc:publisher>TIB Open Publishing (Technische Informationsbibliothek (TIB))</dc:publisher>
          <dc:type>status-type:publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:article</dc:type>
          <dcterms:license>TIB_OJS_Lizenzvereinbarung</dcterms:license>
          <dc:language>en-US</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</dc:rights>
        </dc:record>
      </mets:xmlData>
    </mets:mdWrap>
  </mets:dmdSec>
  <mets:amdSec xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="ie-amd">
    <mets:techMD ID="ie-amd-tech">
      <mets:mdWrap MDTYPE="OTHER" OTHERMDTYPE="dnx">
        <mets:xmlData>
          <dnx xmlns="http://www.exlibrisgroup.com/dps/dnx">
            <section id="generalIECharacteristics">
              <record>
                <key id="status">ACTIVE</key>
                <key id="IEEntityType">Article</key>
                <key id="UserDefinedA">OJS_born-digital</key>
              </record>
            </section>
          </dnx>
        </mets:xmlData>
      </mets:mdWrap>
    </mets:techMD>
    <mets:sourceMD xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="ie-amd-source-1">
      <mets:mdWrap xmlns:mets="http://www.loc.gov/METS/" MDTYPE="MODS">
        <mets:xmlData>
          <mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-7.xsd" version="3.7">
            <mods:titleInfo>
              <mods:title xml:lang="en_US">  Optimizing Reinforcement</mods:title>
              <mods:subTitle xml:lang="en_US">Structural Analysis, Challenges and Strategies</mods:subTitle>
            </mods:titleInfo>
            <mods:abstract xml:lang="en_US">&lt;p&gt;The combination of parametric modelling with structural analysis prompted new synergies between designing and engineering. The connection of structural calculation models such as &lt;em&gt;Karamba3d&lt;/em&gt; to algorithmic modelling platforms such as &lt;em&gt;Grasshopper3d&lt;/em&gt; allowed to embed tools for analysis and simulation into the environment of creative design processes. &lt;br&gt;This way structural analysis advanced from its single sided calculation “duty” towards participation in design language of articulated structural expression. &lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;3d-concrete-printing serves as a great new territory to apply the potential of real-time parametric structural analysis in the built environment of rapid prototyping and robotic fabrication. While 3d-printed-concrete rapidly advanced in technology and empiric know-how, so also grew the ambition to utilize them for larger purposes and bigger building projects. &lt;br&gt;Known requirements such as structural integrity according to building code, interfaces for construction or waterproofing pose clear challenges for further realizations. &lt;br&gt;In order to develop 3d-concrete-printing to its full potential all challenges must serve as opportunities to dissect and rethink established norms and practices, and to construct a new interdisciplinary rule book for an emerging building technology. &lt;br&gt;In this field working through challenges via prototypes serve as great basis for development and allows for an applied discourse within the wider community. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Furthermore to address challenges a flexible toolbox for structural analysis such as &lt;em&gt;Karamba3d&lt;/em&gt; offers the potential to serve as an open instrument for structural analysis and to promote 3d-concrete-printing within that interdisciplinary effort to its next level. On the one hand the tool enables to suggest customized and optimized rebar layouts which could support the development of 3D-concrete-printing further. By enabling this more customizable calculation and tailored real time feedback for complex structures, solutions can develop more structurally informed. On the other hand, recent developments with Karamba3D within our office of Bollinger+Grohmann have shown the possibility of real time feedback loops between the physical printing process and the digital calculation model. &lt;br&gt;Both developments show the potential that material systems can be optimized towards specific patterns or values of forces, or structures can be evaluated in real time for their load bearing capacity while hardening during printing.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</mods:abstract>
            <mods:name type="personal">
              <mods:namePart xml:lang="en_US" type="family">Orlinski</mods:namePart>
              <mods:namePart xml:lang="en_US" type="given">Adam</mods:namePart>
              <mods:affiliation xml:lang="en_US">Bollinger+Grohmann</mods:affiliation>
              <mods:description/>
              <mods:displayForm/>
              <mods:role>
                <mods:roleTerm xml:lang="en_US" type="text">Author</mods:roleTerm>
                <mods:roleTerm xml:lang="en_US" type="code">AU</mods:roleTerm>
              </mods:role>
              <mods:affiliation script="country">AT</mods:affiliation>
            </mods:name>
            <mods:name type="personal">
              <mods:namePart xml:lang="en_US" type="family">De Rycke</mods:namePart>
              <mods:namePart xml:lang="en_US" type="given">Klaas </mods:namePart>
              <mods:affiliation xml:lang="en_US">National School of Architecture of Versailles </mods:affiliation>
              <mods:description xml:lang="en_US"/>
              <mods:displayForm xml:lang="en_US"/>
              <mods:role>
                <mods:roleTerm xml:lang="en_US" type="text">Author</mods:roleTerm>
                <mods:roleTerm xml:lang="en_US" type="code">AU</mods:roleTerm>
              </mods:role>
              <mods:affiliation script="country">FR</mods:affiliation>
            </mods:name>
            <mods:name type="personal">
              <mods:namePart xml:lang="en_US" type="family">Heimrath</mods:namePart>
              <mods:namePart xml:lang="en_US" type="given">Moritz</mods:namePart>
              <mods:affiliation xml:lang="en_US">University of Applied Arts Vienna </mods:affiliation>
              <mods:description xml:lang="en_US"/>
              <mods:displayForm xml:lang="en_US"/>
              <mods:role>
                <mods:roleTerm xml:lang="en_US" type="text">Author</mods:roleTerm>
                <mods:roleTerm xml:lang="en_US" type="code">AU</mods:roleTerm>
              </mods:role>
              <mods:affiliation script="country">AT</mods:affiliation>
            </mods:name>
            <mods:subject xml:lang="en_US" authority="keywords">Optimization</mods:subject>
            <mods:subject xml:lang="en_US" authority="keywords">Parametric Engineering</mods:subject>
            <mods:subject xml:lang="en_US" authority="keywords">Force-Flow</mods:subject>
            <mods:subject xml:lang="en_US" authority="keywords">3d-Concrete-Printing</mods:subject>
            <mods:location displayLabel="coverage"/>
            <mods:accessCondition displayLabel="rights"/>
            <mods:identifier type="doi"/>
            <mods:recordInfo>
              <mods:recordContentSource/>
            </mods:recordInfo>
            <mods:originInfo>
              <mods:publisher xml:lang="en_US">Adam Orlinski, Klaas  De Rycke, Moritz Heimrath</mods:publisher>
            </mods:originInfo>
            <mods:genre/>
            <mods:relatedItem type="host" displayLabel="OCP">
              <extension>
                <abbreviation xml:lang="en_US">Open Conf Proc</abbreviation>
                <acronym xml:lang="en_US">OCP</acronym>
                <authorInformation xml:lang="de_DE">Haben Sie Interesse, einen Beitrag bei dieser Zeitschrift einzureichen? Wir möchten Sie auf &lt;a href="http://ojs22.service.tib.eu/ojs/index.php/ocp/about"&gt;Über uns&lt;/a&gt;, wo Sie die Richtlinien der Zeitschrift einsehen können, und auf &lt;a href="http://ojs22.service.tib.eu/ojs/index.php/ocp/about/submissions#authorGuidelines"&gt;Richtlinien für Autor/innen&lt;/a&gt; verweisen. Autor/innen müssen sich &lt;a href="http://ojs22.service.tib.eu/ojs/index.php/ocp/user/register"&gt;registrieren&lt;/a&gt;, bevor Sie einen Beitrag bei der Zeitschrift einreichen können. Falls Sie bereits angemeldet sind, einfach &lt;a href="http://ojs22.service.tib.eu/ojs/index.php/ocp/login"&gt;einloggen&lt;/a&gt; und die "Fünf Schritte zur Einreichung" abarbeiten.</authorInformation>
                <authorInformation xml:lang="en_US">Interested in submitting to this journal? We recommend that you review the &lt;a href="http://ojs22.service.tib.eu/ojs/index.php/ocp/about"&gt;About the Journal&lt;/a&gt; page for the journal's section policies, as well as the &lt;a href="http://ojs22.service.tib.eu/ojs/index.php/ocp/about/submissions#authorGuidelines"&gt;Author Guidelines&lt;/a&gt;. Authors need to &lt;a href="http://ojs22.service.tib.eu/ojs/index.php/ocp/user/register"&gt;register&lt;/a&gt; with the journal prior to submitting or, if already registered, can simply &lt;a href="http://ojs22.service.tib.eu/ojs/index.php/index/login"&gt;log in&lt;/a&gt; and begin the five-step process.</authorInformation>
                <librarianInformation xml:lang="de_DE">Wir ermutigen Forschungsbibliotheken, diese Zeitschrift in die Liste ihrer elektronischen Zeitschriften aufzunehmen. Darüber hinaus bietet das Open Source Veröffentlichungssystem dieser Zeitschrift Bibliotheken die Möglichkeit, Zeitschriften, an denen Mitglieder ihrer Fakultät mitarbeiten, online bereitzustellen. Siehe &lt;a href="http://pkp.sfu.ca"&gt;Public Knowledge Project&lt;/a&gt;.</librarianInformation>
                <librarianInformation xml:lang="en_US">We encourage research librarians to list this journal among their library's electronic journal holdings. As well, it may be worth noting that this journal's open source publishing system is suitable for libraries to host for their faculty members to use with journals they are involved in editing (see &lt;a href="http://pkp.sfu.ca/ojs"&gt;Open Journal Systems&lt;/a&gt;).</librarianInformation>
                <lockssLicense xml:lang="de_DE">Diese Zeitschrift verwendet das LOCKSS-System, um mit Hilfe der teilnehmenden Bibliotheken ein dezentralen Achivierungssystem zu schaffen, bei dem diese Bibliotheken die Zeitschrift zu Aufbewahrungs- und Wiederherstellungszwecken permanent archivieren. &lt;a href="http://www.lockss.org/"&gt;Mehr...&lt;/a&gt;</lockssLicense>
                <lockssLicense xml:lang="en_US">This journal utilizes the LOCKSS system to create a distributed archiving system among participating libraries and permits those libraries to create permanent archives of the journal for purposes of preservation and restoration. &lt;a href="http://www.lockss.org/"&gt;More...&lt;/a&gt;</lockssLicense>
                <openAccessPolicy xml:lang="de_DE">Diese Zeitschrift bietet freien Zugang (Open Access) zu ihren Inhalten, entsprechend der Grundannahme, dass die freie öffentliche Verfügbarkeit von Forschung einem weltweiten Wissensaustausch zugute kommt.</openAccessPolicy>
                <openAccessPolicy xml:lang="en_US">This journal provides immediate open access to its content on the principle that making research freely available to the public supports a greater global exchange of knowledge.</openAccessPolicy>
                <privacyStatement xml:lang="de_DE">&lt;p&gt;Namen und E-Mail-Adressen, die auf den Webseiten der Zeitschrift eingegeben werden, werden ausschließlich zu den angegebenen Zwecken verwendet und nicht an Dritte weitergegeben.&lt;/p&gt;</privacyStatement>
                <privacyStatement xml:lang="en_US">&lt;p&gt;The user (author, editor, or reviewer) agrees to the processing of his/her personal data provided to Technische Informationsbibliothek (TIB) in accordance with the &lt;a href="https://www.tib-op.org/ojs/index.php/index/tibop/privacystatement"&gt;data protection declaration&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="https://www.tib-op.org/ojs/plugins/themes/tibTheme/assets/files/20210222_TIBOpenPublishing_infosheetdataprotection_OJS_final_v2.pdf"&gt;infosheet data protection&lt;/a&gt;. The data is processed exclusively by TIB in order to provide the service of TIB Open Publishing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Confidentiality Agreement [1]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the publishing process you will have access to personal data such as name, contact data, institutional affiliation, possibly preffered public name, email signature, telephone number, postal address, profile picture, short biography, URL of homepage, ORCID and publication-related information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The principles of Article 5 (1) GDPR must be observed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personal data&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;may only be processed if the &lt;strong&gt;data subject has given consent or if a statutory provision so permits. &lt;/strong&gt;The processing must be comprehensible for the data subject ("transparency").&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;may only be collected for &lt;strong&gt;specified, explicit and legitimate purposes. &lt;/strong&gt;They may not be further processed for any other purpose unless this is explicitly permitted ("purpose limitation").&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;may only be processed in the &lt;strong&gt;amount and &lt;/strong&gt;to&lt;strong&gt; the extent appropriate and necessary &lt;/strong&gt;for &lt;strong&gt;the purpose &lt;/strong&gt;("data minimisation").&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;must be &lt;strong&gt;accurate and, as far as possible, kept up to date&lt;/strong&gt;; every reasonable step must be taken to ensure that data that are inaccurate are erased or rectified without delay ('accuracy').&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;may &lt;strong&gt;only &lt;/strong&gt;be &lt;strong&gt;stored for the amount of time &lt;/strong&gt;necessary to achieve the purpose of storage and must then be anonymised or erased ("storage limitation").&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;must be protected by &lt;strong&gt;technical and organisational measures in &lt;/strong&gt;such a way as to ensure &lt;strong&gt;appropriate security &lt;/strong&gt;against unauthorised or unlawful processing or loss/destruction/damage ("integrity and confidentiality").  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;may &lt;strong&gt;only &lt;/strong&gt;be processed in &lt;strong&gt;accordance with the instructions of the Controller &lt;/strong&gt;(TIB or external client). In addition to individual instructions from superiors, these may also be includeded in process descriptions, flow charts, works agreements, general service instructions as well as company documentation and manuals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Agreement shall continue to apply after the termination of the activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I confirm to be bound by this Agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Art. 5 GDPR, Lower Saxony Data Protection Act (NDSG) of 16 May 2018 as amended from time to time.&lt;/p&gt;</privacyStatement>
                <readerInformation xml:lang="de_DE">Wir empfehlen unseren Leser/innen, sich für die Benachrichtigung bei neuen Veröffentlichungen dieser Zeitschrift einzutragen. Verwenden Sie den &lt;a href="http://ojs22.service.tib.eu/ojs/index.php/ocp/user/register"&gt;Registrieren&lt;/a&gt;-Link oben auf der Startseite der Zeitschrift. Angemeldete Leser/innen erhalten zu jeder neuen Ausgabe der Zeitschrift die Inhaltsangabe per E-Mail zugeschickt. Die Anmeldung ermöglicht es gleichzeitig der Zeitschrift, einen gewissen Grad an Unterstützung oder eine gewisse Leser/innenschaft zu belegen. Siehe die Regelungen zum &lt;a href="http://ojs22.service.tib.eu/ojs/index.php/ocp/about/submissions#privacyStatement"&gt;Schutz personenbezogener Daten&lt;/a&gt; der Zeitschrift, die sicherstellen, dass weder Namen noch E-Mail-Adressen registrierter Benutzer/innen zu anderen Zwecken verwendet werden.</readerInformation>
                <readerInformation xml:lang="en_US">We encourage readers to sign up for the publishing notification service for this journal. Use the &lt;a href="http://ojs22.service.tib.eu/ojs/index.php/ocp/user/register"&gt;Register&lt;/a&gt; link at the top of the home page for the journal. This registration will result in the reader receiving the Table of Contents by email for each new issue of the journal. This list also allows the journal to claim a certain level of support or readership. See the journal's &lt;a href="http://ojs22.service.tib.eu/ojs/index.php/ocp/about/submissions#privacyStatement"&gt;Privacy Statement&lt;/a&gt;, which assures readers that their name and email address will not be used for other purposes.</readerInformation>
                <searchDescription xml:lang="en_US">Open Conference Proceedings are the home for various open-access proceedings of conferences organized by different institutions.</searchDescription>
                <supportedLocales xml:lang="1">en_US</supportedLocales>
                <supportedSubmissionLocales xml:lang="0">en_US</supportedSubmissionLocales>
              </extension>
            </mods:relatedItem>
          </mods:mods>
        </mets:xmlData>
      </mets:mdWrap>
    </mets:sourceMD>
  </mets:amdSec>
  <mets:amdSec ID="rep1-amd">
    <mets:techMD ID="rep1-amd-tech">
      <mets:mdWrap MDTYPE="OTHER" OTHERMDTYPE="dnx">
        <mets:xmlData>
          <dnx xmlns="http://www.exlibrisgroup.com/dps/dnx">
            <section id="generalRepCharacteristics">
              <record>
                <key id="preservationType">PRESERVATION_MASTER</key>
                <key id="usageType">VIEW</key>
                <key id="RevisionNumber">0</key>
              </record>
            </section>
          </dnx>
        </mets:xmlData>
      </mets:mdWrap>
    </mets:techMD>
  </mets:amdSec>
  <mets:amdSec ID="fid1-1-amd">
    <mets:techMD ID="fid1-1-amd-tech">
      <mets:mdWrap MDTYPE="OTHER" OTHERMDTYPE="dnx">
        <mets:xmlData>
          <dnx xmlns="http://www.exlibrisgroup.com/dps/dnx">
            <section id="generalFileCharacteristics">
              <record>
                <key id="fileOriginalPath">/ocp-83-v1/content/streams/MASTER/83-27-2093-1-10-20220124.xml</key>
              </record>
            </section>
            <section id="fileFixity">
              <record>
                <key id="fixityType">MD5</key>
                <key id="fixityValue">f27029a414dedfb8f766bd1df7dcf54f</key>
              </record>
            </section>
          </dnx>
        </mets:xmlData>
      </mets:mdWrap>
    </mets:techMD>
  </mets:amdSec>
  <mets:amdSec ID="fid2-1-amd">
    <mets:techMD ID="fid2-1-amd-tech">
      <mets:mdWrap MDTYPE="OTHER" OTHERMDTYPE="dnx">
        <mets:xmlData>
          <dnx xmlns="http://www.exlibrisgroup.com/dps/dnx">
            <section id="generalFileCharacteristics">
              <record>
                <key id="fileOriginalPath">/ocp-83-v1/content/streams/MASTER/83-39-2516-1-10-20220211.pdf</key>
              </record>
            </section>
            <section id="fileFixity">
              <record>
                <key id="fixityType">MD5</key>
                <key id="fixityValue">64eda551c7f56a297be659bdcd517931</key>
              </record>
            </section>
          </dnx>
        </mets:xmlData>
      </mets:mdWrap>
    </mets:techMD>
  </mets:amdSec>
  <mets:structMap ID="rep1-1" TYPE="PHYSICAL">
    <mets:div LABEL="Preservation Master">
      <mets:div LABEL="rep1">
        <mets:div LABEL="" TYPE="FILE">
          <mets:fptr FILEID="fid1-1"/>
        </mets:div>
        <mets:div LABEL="" TYPE="FILE">
          <mets:fptr FILEID="fid2-1"/>
        </mets:div>
      </mets:div>
    </mets:div>
  </mets:structMap>
  <mets:fileSec>
    <mets:fileGrp ID="rep1" ADMID="rep1-amd">
      <mets:file ID="fid1-1" ADMID="fid1-1-amd">
        <mets:FLocat xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" LOCTYPE="URL" xlink:href="file://MASTER/83-27-2093-1-10-20220124.xml"/>
      </mets:file>
      <mets:file ID="fid2-1" ADMID="fid2-1-amd">
        <mets:FLocat xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" LOCTYPE="URL" xlink:href="file://MASTER/83-39-2516-1-10-20220211.pdf"/>
      </mets:file>
    </mets:fileGrp>
  </mets:fileSec>
</mets:mets>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mets:mets xmlns:mets="http://www.loc.gov/METS/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <mets:dmdSec xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" ID="ie-dmd">
    <mets:mdWrap MDTYPE="DC">
      <mets:xmlData>
        <dc:record xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
          <dc:title> Optimizing Reinforcement</dc:title>
          <dc:creator>Adam Orlinski</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Klaas  De Rycke</dc:creator>
          <dc:creator>Moritz Heimrath</dc:creator>
          <dc:date>2022-02-15</dc:date>
          <dcterms:isPartOf>Open Access E-Journals/TIB OP/OCP/2021/1/1/</dcterms:isPartOf>
          <dcterms:abstract xml:lang="en_US">The combination of parametric modelling with structural analysis prompted new synergies between designing and engineering. The connection of structural calculation models such as Karamba3d to algorithmic modelling platforms such as Grasshopper3d allowed to embed tools for analysis and simulation into the environment of creative design processes. This way structural analysis advanced from its single sided calculation “duty” towards participation in design language of articulated structural expression.  3d-concrete-printing serves as a great new territory to apply the potential of real-time parametric structural analysis in the built environment of rapid prototyping and robotic fabrication. While 3d-printed-concrete rapidly advanced in technology and empiric know-how, so also grew the ambition to utilize them for larger purposes and bigger building projects. Known requirements such as structural integrity according to building code, interfaces for construction or waterproofing pose clear challenges for further realizations. In order to develop 3d-concrete-printing to its full potential all challenges must serve as opportunities to dissect and rethink established norms and practices, and to construct a new interdisciplinary rule book for an emerging building technology. In this field working through challenges via prototypes serve as great basis for development and allows for an applied discourse within the wider community. Furthermore to address challenges a flexible toolbox for structural analysis such as Karamba3d offers the potential to serve as an open instrument for structural analysis and to promote 3d-concrete-printing within that interdisciplinary effort to its next level. On the one hand the tool enables to suggest customized and optimized rebar layouts which could support the development of 3D-concrete-printing further. By enabling this more customizable calculation and tailored real time feedback for complex structures, solutions can develop more structurally informed. On the other hand, recent developments with Karamba3D within our office of Bollinger+Grohmann have shown the possibility of real time feedback loops between the physical printing process and the digital calculation model. Both developments show the potential that material systems can be optimized towards specific patterns or values of forces, or structures can be evaluated in real time for their load bearing capacity while hardening during printing.</dcterms:abstract>
          <dcterms:issued>2022</dcterms:issued>
          <dcterms:modified>2022-02-15 08:22:42</dcterms:modified>
          <dc:publisher>TIB Open Publishing (Technische Informationsbibliothek (TIB))</dc:publisher>
          <dc:type>status-type:publishedVersion</dc:type>
          <dc:type>doc-type:article</dc:type>
          <dcterms:license>TIB_OJS_Lizenzvereinbarung</dcterms:license>
          <dc:language>en-US</dc:language>
          <dc:rights>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</dc:rights>
        </dc:record>
      </mets:xmlData>
    </mets:mdWrap>
  </mets:dmdSec>
  <mets:amdSec xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="ie-amd">
    <mets:techMD ID="ie-amd-tech">
      <mets:mdWrap MDTYPE="OTHER" OTHERMDTYPE="dnx">
        <mets:xmlData>
          <dnx xmlns="http://www.exlibrisgroup.com/dps/dnx">
            <section id="generalIECharacteristics">
              <record>
                <key id="status">ACTIVE</key>
                <key id="IEEntityType">Article</key>
                <key id="UserDefinedA">OJS_born-digital</key>
              </record>
            </section>
          </dnx>
        </mets:xmlData>
      </mets:mdWrap>
    </mets:techMD>
    <mets:sourceMD xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="ie-amd-source-1">
      <mets:mdWrap xmlns:mets="http://www.loc.gov/METS/" MDTYPE="MODS">
        <mets:xmlData>
          <mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-7.xsd" version="3.7">
            <mods:titleInfo>
              <mods:title xml:lang="en_US">  Optimizing Reinforcement</mods:title>
              <mods:subTitle xml:lang="en_US">Structural Analysis, Challenges and Strategies</mods:subTitle>
            </mods:titleInfo>
            <mods:abstract xml:lang="en_US">&lt;p&gt;The combination of parametric modelling with structural analysis prompted new synergies between designing and engineering. The connection of structural calculation models such as &lt;em&gt;Karamba3d&lt;/em&gt; to algorithmic modelling platforms such as &lt;em&gt;Grasshopper3d&lt;/em&gt; allowed to embed tools for analysis and simulation into the environment of creative design processes. &lt;br&gt;This way structural analysis advanced from its single sided calculation “duty” towards participation in design language of articulated structural expression. &lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;3d-concrete-printing serves as a great new territory to apply the potential of real-time parametric structural analysis in the built environment of rapid prototyping and robotic fabrication. While 3d-printed-concrete rapidly advanced in technology and empiric know-how, so also grew the ambition to utilize them for larger purposes and bigger building projects. &lt;br&gt;Known requirements such as structural integrity according to building code, interfaces for construction or waterproofing pose clear challenges for further realizations. &lt;br&gt;In order to develop 3d-concrete-printing to its full potential all challenges must serve as opportunities to dissect and rethink established norms and practices, and to construct a new interdisciplinary rule book for an emerging building technology. &lt;br&gt;In this field working through challenges via prototypes serve as great basis for development and allows for an applied discourse within the wider community. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Furthermore to address challenges a flexible toolbox for structural analysis such as &lt;em&gt;Karamba3d&lt;/em&gt; offers the potential to serve as an open instrument for structural analysis and to promote 3d-concrete-printing within that interdisciplinary effort to its next level. On the one hand the tool enables to suggest customized and optimized rebar layouts which could support the development of 3D-concrete-printing further. By enabling this more customizable calculation and tailored real time feedback for complex structures, solutions can develop more structurally informed. On the other hand, recent developments with Karamba3D within our office of Bollinger+Grohmann have shown the possibility of real time feedback loops between the physical printing process and the digital calculation model. &lt;br&gt;Both developments show the potential that material systems can be optimized towards specific patterns or values of forces, or structures can be evaluated in real time for their load bearing capacity while hardening during printing.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</mods:abstract>
            <mods:name type="personal">
              <mods:namePart xml:lang="en_US" type="family">Orlinski</mods:namePart>
              <mods:namePart xml:lang="en_US" type="given">Adam</mods:namePart>
              <mods:affiliation xml:lang="en_US">Bollinger+Grohmann</mods:affiliation>
              <mods:description/>
              <mods:displayForm/>
              <mods:role>
                <mods:roleTerm xml:lang="en_US" type="text">Author</mods:roleTerm>
                <mods:roleTerm xml:lang="en_US" type="code">AU</mods:roleTerm>
              </mods:role>
              <mods:affiliation script="country">AT</mods:affiliation>
            </mods:name>
            <mods:name type="personal">
              <mods:namePart xml:lang="en_US" type="family">De Rycke</mods:namePart>
              <mods:namePart xml:lang="en_US" type="given">Klaas </mods:namePart>
              <mods:affiliation xml:lang="en_US">National School of Architecture of Versailles </mods:affiliation>
              <mods:description xml:lang="en_US"/>
              <mods:displayForm xml:lang="en_US"/>
              <mods:role>
                <mods:roleTerm xml:lang="en_US" type="text">Author</mods:roleTerm>
                <mods:roleTerm xml:lang="en_US" type="code">AU</mods:roleTerm>
              </mods:role>
              <mods:affiliation script="country">FR</mods:affiliation>
            </mods:name>
            <mods:name type="personal">
              <mods:namePart xml:lang="en_US" type="family">Heimrath</mods:namePart>
              <mods:namePart xml:lang="en_US" type="given">Moritz</mods:namePart>
              <mods:affiliation xml:lang="en_US">University of Applied Arts Vienna </mods:affiliation>
              <mods:description xml:lang="en_US"/>
              <mods:displayForm xml:lang="en_US"/>
              <mods:role>
                <mods:roleTerm xml:lang="en_US" type="text">Author</mods:roleTerm>
                <mods:roleTerm xml:lang="en_US" type="code">AU</mods:roleTerm>
              </mods:role>
              <mods:affiliation script="country">AT</mods:affiliation>
            </mods:name>
            <mods:subject xml:lang="en_US" authority="keywords">Optimization</mods:subject>
            <mods:subject xml:lang="en_US" authority="keywords">Parametric Engineering</mods:subject>
            <mods:subject xml:lang="en_US" authority="keywords">Force-Flow</mods:subject>
            <mods:subject xml:lang="en_US" authority="keywords">3d-Concrete-Printing</mods:subject>
            <mods:location displayLabel="coverage"/>
            <mods:accessCondition displayLabel="rights"/>
            <mods:identifier type="doi"/>
            <mods:recordInfo>
              <mods:recordContentSource/>
            </mods:recordInfo>
            <mods:originInfo>
              <mods:publisher xml:lang="en_US">Adam Orlinski, Klaas  De Rycke, Moritz Heimrath</mods:publisher>
            </mods:originInfo>
            <mods:genre/>
            <mods:relatedItem type="host" displayLabel="OCP">
              <extension>
                <abbreviation xml:lang="en_US">Open Conf Proc</abbreviation>
                <acronym xml:lang="en_US">OCP</acronym>
                <authorInformation xml:lang="de_DE">Haben Sie Interesse, einen Beitrag bei dieser Zeitschrift einzureichen? Wir möchten Sie auf &lt;a href="http://ojs22.service.tib.eu/ojs/index.php/ocp/about"&gt;Über uns&lt;/a&gt;, wo Sie die Richtlinien der Zeitschrift einsehen können, und auf &lt;a href="http://ojs22.service.tib.eu/ojs/index.php/ocp/about/submissions#authorGuidelines"&gt;Richtlinien für Autor/innen&lt;/a&gt; verweisen. Autor/innen müssen sich &lt;a href="http://ojs22.service.tib.eu/ojs/index.php/ocp/user/register"&gt;registrieren&lt;/a&gt;, bevor Sie einen Beitrag bei der Zeitschrift einreichen können. Falls Sie bereits angemeldet sind, einfach &lt;a href="http://ojs22.service.tib.eu/ojs/index.php/ocp/login"&gt;einloggen&lt;/a&gt; und die "Fünf Schritte zur Einreichung" abarbeiten.</authorInformation>
                <authorInformation xml:lang="en_US">Interested in submitting to this journal? We recommend that you review the &lt;a href="http://ojs22.service.tib.eu/ojs/index.php/ocp/about"&gt;About the Journal&lt;/a&gt; page for the journal's section policies, as well as the &lt;a href="http://ojs22.service.tib.eu/ojs/index.php/ocp/about/submissions#authorGuidelines"&gt;Author Guidelines&lt;/a&gt;. Authors need to &lt;a href="http://ojs22.service.tib.eu/ojs/index.php/ocp/user/register"&gt;register&lt;/a&gt; with the journal prior to submitting or, if already registered, can simply &lt;a href="http://ojs22.service.tib.eu/ojs/index.php/index/login"&gt;log in&lt;/a&gt; and begin the five-step process.</authorInformation>
                <librarianInformation xml:lang="de_DE">Wir ermutigen Forschungsbibliotheken, diese Zeitschrift in die Liste ihrer elektronischen Zeitschriften aufzunehmen. Darüber hinaus bietet das Open Source Veröffentlichungssystem dieser Zeitschrift Bibliotheken die Möglichkeit, Zeitschriften, an denen Mitglieder ihrer Fakultät mitarbeiten, online bereitzustellen. Siehe &lt;a href="http://pkp.sfu.ca"&gt;Public Knowledge Project&lt;/a&gt;.</librarianInformation>
                <librarianInformation xml:lang="en_US">We encourage research librarians to list this journal among their library's electronic journal holdings. As well, it may be worth noting that this journal's open source publishing system is suitable for libraries to host for their faculty members to use with journals they are involved in editing (see &lt;a href="http://pkp.sfu.ca/ojs"&gt;Open Journal Systems&lt;/a&gt;).</librarianInformation>
                <lockssLicense xml:lang="de_DE">Diese Zeitschrift verwendet das LOCKSS-System, um mit Hilfe der teilnehmenden Bibliotheken ein dezentralen Achivierungssystem zu schaffen, bei dem diese Bibliotheken die Zeitschrift zu Aufbewahrungs- und Wiederherstellungszwecken permanent archivieren. &lt;a href="http://www.lockss.org/"&gt;Mehr...&lt;/a&gt;</lockssLicense>
                <lockssLicense xml:lang="en_US">This journal utilizes the LOCKSS system to create a distributed archiving system among participating libraries and permits those libraries to create permanent archives of the journal for purposes of preservation and restoration. &lt;a href="http://www.lockss.org/"&gt;More...&lt;/a&gt;</lockssLicense>
                <openAccessPolicy xml:lang="de_DE">Diese Zeitschrift bietet freien Zugang (Open Access) zu ihren Inhalten, entsprechend der Grundannahme, dass die freie öffentliche Verfügbarkeit von Forschung einem weltweiten Wissensaustausch zugute kommt.</openAccessPolicy>
                <openAccessPolicy xml:lang="en_US">This journal provides immediate open access to its content on the principle that making research freely available to the public supports a greater global exchange of knowledge.</openAccessPolicy>
                <privacyStatement xml:lang="de_DE">&lt;p&gt;Namen und E-Mail-Adressen, die auf den Webseiten der Zeitschrift eingegeben werden, werden ausschließlich zu den angegebenen Zwecken verwendet und nicht an Dritte weitergegeben.&lt;/p&gt;</privacyStatement>
                <privacyStatement xml:lang="en_US">&lt;p&gt;The user (author, editor, or reviewer) agrees to the processing of his/her personal data provided to Technische Informationsbibliothek (TIB) in accordance with the &lt;a href="https://www.tib-op.org/ojs/index.php/index/tibop/privacystatement"&gt;data protection declaration&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="https://www.tib-op.org/ojs/plugins/themes/tibTheme/assets/files/20210222_TIBOpenPublishing_infosheetdataprotection_OJS_final_v2.pdf"&gt;infosheet data protection&lt;/a&gt;. The data is processed exclusively by TIB in order to provide the service of TIB Open Publishing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Confidentiality Agreement [1]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the publishing process you will have access to personal data such as name, contact data, institutional affiliation, possibly preffered public name, email signature, telephone number, postal address, profile picture, short biography, URL of homepage, ORCID and publication-related information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The principles of Article 5 (1) GDPR must be observed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personal data&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;may only be processed if the &lt;strong&gt;data subject has given consent or if a statutory provision so permits. &lt;/strong&gt;The processing must be comprehensible for the data subject ("transparency").&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;may only be collected for &lt;strong&gt;specified, explicit and legitimate purposes. &lt;/strong&gt;They may not be further processed for any other purpose unless this is explicitly permitted ("purpose limitation").&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;may only be processed in the &lt;strong&gt;amount and &lt;/strong&gt;to&lt;strong&gt; the extent appropriate and necessary &lt;/strong&gt;for &lt;strong&gt;the purpose &lt;/strong&gt;("data minimisation").&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;must be &lt;strong&gt;accurate and, as far as possible, kept up to date&lt;/strong&gt;; every reasonable step must be taken to ensure that data that are inaccurate are erased or rectified without delay ('accuracy').&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;may &lt;strong&gt;only &lt;/strong&gt;be &lt;strong&gt;stored for the amount of time &lt;/strong&gt;necessary to achieve the purpose of storage and must then be anonymised or erased ("storage limitation").&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;must be protected by &lt;strong&gt;technical and organisational measures in &lt;/strong&gt;such a way as to ensure &lt;strong&gt;appropriate security &lt;/strong&gt;against unauthorised or unlawful processing or loss/destruction/damage ("integrity and confidentiality").  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;may &lt;strong&gt;only &lt;/strong&gt;be processed in &lt;strong&gt;accordance with the instructions of the Controller &lt;/strong&gt;(TIB or external client). In addition to individual instructions from superiors, these may also be includeded in process descriptions, flow charts, works agreements, general service instructions as well as company documentation and manuals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Agreement shall continue to apply after the termination of the activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I confirm to be bound by this Agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Art. 5 GDPR, Lower Saxony Data Protection Act (NDSG) of 16 May 2018 as amended from time to time.&lt;/p&gt;</privacyStatement>
                <readerInformation xml:lang="de_DE">Wir empfehlen unseren Leser/innen, sich für die Benachrichtigung bei neuen Veröffentlichungen dieser Zeitschrift einzutragen. Verwenden Sie den &lt;a href="http://ojs22.service.tib.eu/ojs/index.php/ocp/user/register"&gt;Registrieren&lt;/a&gt;-Link oben auf der Startseite der Zeitschrift. Angemeldete Leser/innen erhalten zu jeder neuen Ausgabe der Zeitschrift die Inhaltsangabe per E-Mail zugeschickt. Die Anmeldung ermöglicht es gleichzeitig der Zeitschrift, einen gewissen Grad an Unterstützung oder eine gewisse Leser/innenschaft zu belegen. Siehe die Regelungen zum &lt;a href="http://ojs22.service.tib.eu/ojs/index.php/ocp/about/submissions#privacyStatement"&gt;Schutz personenbezogener Daten&lt;/a&gt; der Zeitschrift, die sicherstellen, dass weder Namen noch E-Mail-Adressen registrierter Benutzer/innen zu anderen Zwecken verwendet werden.</readerInformation>
                <readerInformation xml:lang="en_US">We encourage readers to sign up for the publishing notification service for this journal. Use the &lt;a href="http://ojs22.service.tib.eu/ojs/index.php/ocp/user/register"&gt;Register&lt;/a&gt; link at the top of the home page for the journal. This registration will result in the reader receiving the Table of Contents by email for each new issue of the journal. This list also allows the journal to claim a certain level of support or readership. See the journal's &lt;a href="http://ojs22.service.tib.eu/ojs/index.php/ocp/about/submissions#privacyStatement"&gt;Privacy Statement&lt;/a&gt;, which assures readers that their name and email address will not be used for other purposes.</readerInformation>
                <searchDescription xml:lang="en_US">Open Conference Proceedings are the home for various open-access proceedings of conferences organized by different institutions.</searchDescription>
                <supportedLocales xml:lang="1">en_US</supportedLocales>
                <supportedSubmissionLocales xml:lang="0">en_US</supportedSubmissionLocales>
              </extension>
            </mods:relatedItem>
          </mods:mods>
        </mets:xmlData>
      </mets:mdWrap>
    </mets:sourceMD>
  </mets:amdSec>
  <mets:amdSec ID="rep1-amd">
    <mets:techMD ID="rep1-amd-tech">
      <mets:mdWrap MDTYPE="OTHER" OTHERMDTYPE="dnx">
        <mets:xmlData>
          <dnx xmlns="http://www.exlibrisgroup.com/dps/dnx">
            <section id="generalRepCharacteristics">
              <record>
                <key id="preservationType">PRESERVATION_MASTER</key>
                <key id="usageType">VIEW</key>
                <key id="RevisionNumber">0</key>
              </record>
            </section>
          </dnx>
        </mets:xmlData>
      </mets:mdWrap>
    </mets:techMD>
  </mets:amdSec>
  <mets:amdSec ID="fid1-1-amd">
    <mets:techMD ID="fid1-1-amd-tech">
      <mets:mdWrap MDTYPE="OTHER" OTHERMDTYPE="dnx">
        <mets:xmlData>
          <dnx xmlns="http://www.exlibrisgroup.com/dps/dnx">
            <section id="generalFileCharacteristics">
              <record>
                <key id="fileOriginalPath">/ocp-83-v1/content/streams/MASTER/83-27-2093-1-10-20220124.xml</key>
              </record>
            </section>
            <section id="fileFixity">
              <record>
                <key id="fixityType">MD5</key>
                <key id="fixityValue">f27029a414dedfb8f766bd1df7dcf54f</key>
              </record>
            </section>
          </dnx>
        </mets:xmlData>
      </mets:mdWrap>
    </mets:techMD>
  </mets:amdSec>
  <mets:amdSec ID="fid2-1-amd">
    <mets:techMD ID="fid2-1-amd-tech">
      <mets:mdWrap MDTYPE="OTHER" OTHERMDTYPE="dnx">
        <mets:xmlData>
          <dnx xmlns="http://www.exlibrisgroup.com/dps/dnx">
            <section id="generalFileCharacteristics">
              <record>
                <key id="fileOriginalPath">/ocp-83-v1/content/streams/MASTER/83-39-2516-1-10-20220211.pdf</key>
              </record>
            </section>
            <section id="fileFixity">
              <record>
                <key id="fixityType">MD5</key>
                <key id="fixityValue">64eda551c7f56a297be659bdcd517931</key>
              </record>
            </section>
          </dnx>
        </mets:xmlData>
      </mets:mdWrap>
    </mets:techMD>
  </mets:amdSec>
  <mets:structMap ID="rep1-1" TYPE="PHYSICAL">
    <mets:div LABEL="Preservation Master">
      <mets:div LABEL="rep1">
        <mets:div LABEL="" TYPE="FILE">
          <mets:fptr FILEID="fid1-1"/>
        </mets:div>
        <mets:div LABEL="" TYPE="FILE">
          <mets:fptr FILEID="fid2-1"/>
        </mets:div>
      </mets:div>
    </mets:div>
  </mets:structMap>
  <mets:fileSec>
    <mets:fileGrp ID="rep1" ADMID="rep1-amd">
      <mets:file ID="fid1-1" ADMID="fid1-1-amd">
        <mets:FLocat xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" LOCTYPE="URL" xlink:href="file://MASTER/83-27-2093-1-10-20220124.xml"/>
      </mets:file>
      <mets:file ID="fid2-1" ADMID="fid2-1-amd">
        <mets:FLocat xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" LOCTYPE="URL" xlink:href="file://MASTER/83-39-2516-1-10-20220211.pdf"/>
      </mets:file>
    </mets:fileGrp>
  </mets:fileSec>
</mets:mets>
